Albert Henry Imlah Papers MS176
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Albert Henry Imlah Papers
1932 -- 1985
1903 -- 2005
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Imlah, Albert Henry
MS176
2.3 Linear Feet 2 document boxes, 1 record carton, 1 oversize folder
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection was physically kept in received order. Intellectual arrangement was imposed by the archivist at the time of processing. There are five series: 1. Books and photographs, 2. Correspondence, 3. Research and Subject Files, and 4. 2016 accessions, and 5. 2021 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
James Albert Henry Imlah was born in 1901 in New Westminster, British Columbia, Canada. He attended University of British Columbia where he earned his A.B. and went on to earn his M.A. at Clark University and his Ph.D. at Harvard University. He became an Instructor in History at Tufts University in 1927 after teaching at the University of Maine. In 1929, he attained the rank of Assistant Professor, and in 1935 he was made a full professor, a position he held until 1956. Imlah held the posts of Professor of Diplomatic History at the Fletcher School and Walter S. Dickson Professor of English and American History, 1958-1970. Upon retiring in 1970, he was granted the status of Professor Emeritus. He was an active member of the American Association of University Professors, including as a member of the national council from 1946-1949 and chair of the its Committee on the Economic Status of the Profession from 1948–1958. Imlah died on July 8, 1989.
In his honor, the Albert H. Imlah European History Prize is given for either distinguished work in the History of Western Civilization course or to promote reading in the honors program, or in comparable programs in history. The Albert H. Imlah Excellence in History Prize is awarded to a senior for excellence in history.
Custodial History
Accession 2011.054 received via the Office of Alumni Relations. Later accessions received from Ann Imlah Schneider, Albert Imlah's daughter. Ms. Schneider did select which items to send - see accession information (2011.064) for more detailed description.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials by and related to Albert H. Imlah, Tufts University professor of economics. Materials date from 1903 – 2005. The collection has photographs of the Tufts campus, Tufts faculty, and the Imlah family. It also includes a number of books written by Albert H. Imlah and Ann G. Imlah, his daughter. The collection also contains correspondence relating to his research and appointment at Tufts University, as well as personal correspondence with his wife, Helen Woodbridge Imlah.
Additionally, there are a number of subject files. These are largely related to his research into nineteenth century trade in Great Britain. They also include articles and book reviews written by Albert H. Imlah; essays written by Miriam B. Imlah, his second wife; personal information regarding Albert and Miriam Imlah; and research conducted for the American Association of University Professors.
Economic history; United States -- History; Faculty papers; Tufts University -- History; University history
- Books and photographs, 1903 -- 1967; MS176.001
  Arrangement
  This series was kept in received order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains books, photographs, and related documentation. The photographs, dated between 1903 and 1954, are of the Imlah family, Tufts faculty and their families, and Tufts scenes. The books in this series include: Economic Elements in the Pax Brittanica: Studies in British Foreign Trade in the Nineteenth Century (1958); Lord Ellenborough: A Biography of Edward Law, Earl of Ellenborough, Governor-General of India (1937); and The Earl of Ellenborough, 1790 -- 1871: A Political Biography (1931). These were all written by Albert H. Imlah, the last of which appears to be his PhD dissertation for Harvard. Additionally, there is a book titled Britain and Switzerland (1966), written by Ann G. Imlah, his daughter. There were additional materials interfiled in each of the books, which were separated into folders. These materials date from 1937 to 1967 and include newspaper clippings, book reviews, and notes.
  - Tufts postcards and photographs, 1932 -- 1949; MS176.001.002.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Open for research.
  - Tufts scenes and other faculty and families, 1932 -- 1954; MS176.001.002.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Imlah family, 1903 -- 1936; MS176.001.003.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - Economic Elements in the Pax Brittanica: Studies in British Foreign Trade in the Nineteenth Century, by Albert H. Imlah, 1958; MS176.001.003.00002; 1 Volumes (Box 3)
  - Documentation removed from Pax Brittanica, circa 1959; MS176.001.003.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - Britain and Switzerland, 1845-60, by Ann G. Imlah, 1966; MS176.001.003.00004; 1 Volumes (Box 3)
  - Documentation removed from Britain and Switzerland, 1967; MS176.001.003.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - Lord Ellenborough: A Biography of Edward Law, Earl of Ellenborough, Governor-General of India, by Albert H. Imlah, 1939; MS176.001.003.00006; 1 Volumes (Box 3)
  - Documentation removed from Lord Ellenborough, 1937 -- 1959; MS176.001.003.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - The Earl of Ellenborough, 1790 -- 1871: A Political Biography, by Albert H. Imlah, dissertation copy, 1931; MS176.001.003.00008; 1 Volumes (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1927 -- 1985; MS176.002
  This series was kept in received order. Intellectually, it is arranged in chronological order.
  This series contains correspondence to and from Albert H. Imlah from 1927 to 1985. While the correspondence varies in subject, it chiefly relates to his research and appointment at Tufts University. Notably, there is also a body of correspondence related to salary research that Imlah completed for the American Association of University Professors.
  - Correspondence: Tufts and Harvard appointments, 1927 -- 1969; MS176.002.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Anna Jacobsen Schwartz, 1941 -- 1942; MS176.002.001.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952 -- 1954; MS176.002.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Ford Foundation, 1954 -- 1956; MS176.002.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1955; MS176.002.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Professional, 1956; MS176.002.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1957; MS176.002.001.00043; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958; MS176.002.001.00042; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959; MS176.002.001.00041; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: American Association of University Professors Committee on the Economic Status of the Profession, 1960; MS176.002.001.00039; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960; MS176.002.001.00040; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961; MS176.002.001.00036; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: American Association of University Professors Report on the Economic Status of the Profession, 1961 -- 1962; MS176.002.001.00038; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962; MS176.002.001.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963; MS176.002.001.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963 -- 1964; MS176.002.001.00037; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1964; MS176.002.001.00032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: American Association of University Professors, Special Committee -- Sayre, 1964; MS176.002.001.00033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965; MS176.002.001.00031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966; MS176.002.001.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967; MS176.002.001.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: American Association of University Professors, 1968 -- 1969; MS176.002.001.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968; MS176.002.001.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; MS176.002.001.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Retirement resolutions on Albert H. Imlah, 1970; MS176.002.001.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970; MS176.002.001.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971; MS176.002.001.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972 -- 1974; MS176.002.001.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975 -- 1985; MS176.002.001.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
- Research and subject files, 1923 -- 2005; MS176.003
  This collection was kept in received order. Intellectually, it is grouped roughly by subject.
  This series contains research and subject files dating from 1923 to 2005. They chiefly consist of research into nineteenth-century trade in Great Britain conducted by Albert H. Imlah in approximately the 1950s. Other major subjects covered by this series include salary research for the American Association of University Professors; personal, financial, and memorial service information for Albert H. Imlah and Miriam B. Imlah, his wife; essays written by Miriam B. Imlah; and book reviews and journal articles written by Albert H. Imlah.
  - American Association of University Presidents report on Tufts salaries, 1947 -- 1952; MS176.003.002.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Weighted mean salaries, 1953 -- 1954; MS176.003.002.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Albert H. Imlah memorial service, 1989; MS176.003.002.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Albert H. Imlah finances, 1935 -- 1992; MS176.003.002.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - 19 Sawyer Ave. deed, 1935; MS176.003.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Miriam B. Imlah memorial service and finances, 1923 -- 2005; MS176.003.002.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Miriam B. Imlah writing group, 1991 -- 1992; MS176.003.002.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Miriam Imlah writing group, 1992 -- 1994; MS176.003.002.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Fletcher Book Fund, 1967 -- 1969; MS176.003.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - American Historical Association paper on Pax Brittanica and Export of Capital, 1949; MS176.003.001.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Book reviews by Albert H. Imlah, 1932 -- 1968; MS176.003.002.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Harvard University Press and reviews, 1957 -- 1986; MS176.003.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Journal publications by Imlah, 1949 -- 1951; MS176.003.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Balance of payments, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Commodity series, 1846 -- 1849, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Real values of commodities, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Real values: imports -- re-exports, 1830 -- 1846, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Real values: summaries, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Tarriff rates, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: commodities receipts, 1796 -- 1902, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: export commodities, 1796 -- 1908, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: export commodities, 1900 -- 1913, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: import commodities, 1885 -- 1902, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: imports, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: imports and re-exports, 1900 -- 1913, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: miscellaneous, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Terms of trade: worksheets, circa 1950; MS176.003.001.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
- 2016 accessions, 1922 -- 1981; MS176.004; 3 Folder(s)
  This series is open for research.
  This series is arranged in received order.
  This series includes Imlah's University of British Columbia yearbook from 1922, his Tufts University honorary doctorate diploma from 1981, and photographs of 19 Sawyer Avenue and the Class of 1922 reunion.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Transferred by Ann Imlah Schneider, 2016, accession 2016.124.
  - University of British Columbia yearbook, 1922; MS176.004.003.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
  - Photographs, circa 1935 -- 1962; MS176.004.003.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3)
    This file includes photographs of 19 Sawyer Avenue taken by Melville Munro from 1935; Class of 1922 reunion photographs circa 1957; and a portrait of Albert Henry Imlah from 1962.
  - Tufts University honorary doctorate diploma, 1981; MS176.004.004; 1 Folder(s) 1 oversize folder (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 10)
- 2021 accessions, 1921 -- 1954; 1921 -- 1925; MS176.000075
  Transferred by Ann Imlah Schneider, 2021, accession UA-2022-005.
  This series is arranged in the order in which it was received.
  This series contains correspondence sent to Albert Henry Imlah, the bulk of which is personal correspondence written and sent by his wife, Helen Woodbridge Imlah. Correspondence from 1954 is primarily condolence cards and messages sent to Imlah after Helen Imlah's death. This series also contains multiple prints of a single portrait of Imlah, his 1921-1922 datebook, and international law and history course exam papers from his time as a student.
  - Correspondence, 1922 -- 1925; MS176.000076; 6 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 1-5, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1954; MS176.000077; 4 Folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 2-4, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Datebook, 1921 -- 1922; MS176.000078; 1 Folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Posed photograph of Albert Henry Imlah, circa 1922; MS176.000079; 1 Folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Exam papers, circa 1922; MS176.000080; 1 Folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 4)